Finding Aid for Victor Hugo Lane Papers, 1897-1929
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Victor Hugo Lane papers, 1897-1929
Lane, Victor Hugo, 1952-1930
4.3 linear ft.
851718 Aa 2
Law professor at the University of Michigan, papers include correspondence relating to his law school activities, his interest in the Presbyterian churches of Adrian, and Ann Arbor, Michigan, the University Student Religious Association, the Young Men's Christian Association the Western Intercollegiate Conference, the Michigan Law Review, and the Uncle Sam Macaroni Co. of Tecumseh, Michigan; and photographs; letter, June 1, 1903, from Gustavus Ohlinger on the Philippines.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Victor Hugo Lane, Jr. (donor no. 48 ) in 1936.
The collection is open to research.
Victor Hugo Lane was the Fletcher Professor of Law at the University of Michigan from 1897-1928. Previously he served a judge of the Michigan First Judicial Circuit Court from 1888-1897.
Lane was born May 27, 185 in Geneva, Ohio to Henry and Clotilda Catherine Sawyer Lane. The family moved to Hudson, Michigan in 1866. Lane enrolled in the University of Michigan in 1879, earning a degree in civil engineering in 1874. After two years of practice, he returned to the university and received a law degree in 1878. While in law school, Lane married Ida M. Knowlton, sister of professor and future dean of the Law School Jerome C. Knowlton. Lane established his first practice in Hudson and later moved to Adrian, from where he was appointed to the circuit court bench.
In addition to his teaching role, Lane was appointed law librarian and served the university in many other capacities including member and chairman of the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, President of the University Alumni Association and President of the University Y.M.C.A. He was also an active member, serving as elder, of the First Presbyterian Church of Ann Arbor.
Lane died January 24, 1930. He is buried in Forest Hills cemetery in Ann Arbor.
The Victor Hugo Lane papers include correspondence relating to his law school activities, his interest in the Presbyterian churches of Adrian and Ann Arbor, the University Student Religious Association, the Young Men's Christian Association, the Western Intercollegiate Conference, the Michigan Law Review, and the Uncle Sam Macaroni Co. of Tecumseh; also letter from Gustavus Ohlinger on the Philippine Islands, June 1, 1903
The papers are organized in to five series; Correspondence, 1898-1929; Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association; First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); and Visual Materials.
The Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association series consists of correspondence, 1906-1907, from Lane's term as Michigan's faculty representative to the conference. It was during this time that a series of reforms, initially proposed by U-M president James B. Angell, led to Michigan's withdrawal from the conference.
Subjects:
Adrian (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.); First Presbyterian Church (Adrian, Mich.); First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Intercollegiate Conference of Faculty Representatives.; Judges--Michigan.; Lane, Victor Hugo, 1852-1930.; Law.; Michigan law review.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Adrian.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Student Christian Association (University of Michigan); Uncle Sam Macaroni Company (Tecumseh, Mich.); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Law School.; Young Men's Christian Associations.
Contributors:
Baird, Charles, 1870-1944.; Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.; Chapin, Roy D. (Roy Dikeman), 1880-1936.; Fletcher, Frank Ward, 1853-1922.; Grant, Claudius Buchanan, 1835-1921.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Knappen, Loyal Edwin, 1854-1930.; Moore, Joseph B., 1845-1930.; Ohlinger, Gustavus, 1877-; Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.; Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926.; Smith, Henry Cassorte, 1859-1911.; Stone, Ralph, 1868-1956.; Turner, Frederick Jackson, 1861-1932.
- Correspondence
  - 1898-June 1905, 54 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1905-April 1912, 37 folders (Box 2)
  - May 1912-December 1918, 50 folders (Box 3)
  - January 1919-December 1929, 36 folders (Box 4)
- Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association
  - Correspondence, 1906-November 1907, 9 folders (Box 4)
- First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
  - Correspondence, January 1910-December 1911, 6 folders (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  - Photograph/autograph album presented to Victor H. Lane by the First Presbyterian Sabbath School of Adrian (Box 5)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Baird, Charles, 1870-1944
ca. 1920-1929
Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949
July 3, 17, 28, Aug. 24, 1903
Chapin, Roy Dikeman, 1880-1936
Aug. 28, 1923
Fletcher, Frank Ward, 1853-1922
Oct. 10, 1908
Grant, Claudius Buchanan, 1835-1921
Feb. 6, 9, 14, 1905
Hutchins, Harry Burns, 1847-1930
Aug. 2, 14, 1901, Aug. 21, 1909, Dec. 29, 1910
Knappen, Loyal Edwin, 1854-1930
Jan.-Feb. 1907
Moore, Joseph B, 1845-1930
Sept. 23, 1901
Ohlinger, Gustavus, 1877-
June 1, 1903
Sawyer, Walter Hulme, 1861-1931
Dec. 9, 1901; Jan. 27, Feb. 17, 1905; Oct. 8, 1907; Jan. 1, May 31, 1911
Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926
Jan. 18, 23, 28, 29, 1907
Smith, Henry Cassorte, 1859-1911
Feb. 21, Apr. 28, 1900, May 5, 1911
Stone, Ralph, 1868-1956
ca. 1921-1929
Turner, Frederick Jackson, 1861-1932
Jan. 19, 1907